I was thinking about this uh practice of
contemplation contemplating for example
the danger and
sensuality or various types of
contemplation can you describe how to do
that like do you yeah recite some things
that you've heard or what do you do
right so so that's like
the the cont lation has to start by
learning what you need to
contemplate so you can you know you can
start on your own but your experience
top to bottom is already affected with a
via already affected with ignorance
which means that contemplation will be
biased will have a like a will contain
contradictions that you're unaware of
and it would be it would not be
necessarily representing the nature of
things how they actually are so in order
for you to start under doing all of
those issues through right contemplation
you need to really learn uh what you
need to contemplate what you need to see
so that's why learning is important
learning for the sake of meaning like
you learn something so to understand
what you need to do and see not just
learn so you have information to counter
somebody else or for the comparison
between different aspects of the of the
sutas and so on sometimes people confuse
learning with just as I said collecting
a vast amount of references and
information and then when they hear one
point they connect it to another point
they heard but it's like well that's
kind of irrelevant what's relevant is
that when you hear one point Have You
developed it have you followed it
through have you contemplated it until
the meaning sunk in and now you know for
yourself or does your contemplation stop
with just comparison between the sutas
and different things that the Buddha
said that you kind of adopted now as the
truth so the the practice of
contemplation then well if you learn it
from the sutas uh one of the first and
most obvious things will be that well
you don't you can't really
contemplate uh accurately the nature of
your experience the nature of Your
Action the nature of wholesome the
nature of unh wholesome unless you begin
to emulate that nature through sense
restraint and keeping the virtue in
other words if you're running around
wild like a wild animal letting letting
your mind go here and there uh letting
your physical Behavior do what it wants
uh that contemplation will not have uh a
fertile ground you might be you might be
pondering about things uh theoretically
abstractly but if you want the meaning
of that contemplation to start affecting
your experience your behavior you need
to start tailoring that behavior
beforehand that's where the virtue comes
first so what I'm basically saying in
simple terms is there is no
contemplation unless you have developing
virtue and sense restraint as its basis
so but say you do you are keeping the
precepts you are celibate uh you are
guarding of the sense do you're watchful
of your intentions well then you
contemplate just take a suta read the
suta see what it talks about and then
try and understand those things for
yourself not well initially it to be on
the level of making sense out of it but
then also like you need to see it for
yourself here and now in this
experience so that's the point of every
suta that's why like technically if you
understand one full suta you can be an
Arun any suta uh so contemplation then
Begins by by by recognizing the
universals from that suta what is
applicable here and now and that's why
most of the sutas they always talk about
that the nature of craving the nature of
assumptions the nature of wrong views
and that is pretty much what you need to
see here and now so you you start
contemplating by in this case you could
just for example say ask yourself why am
I
suffering so asking right questions is
the beginning of successful
contemplation uh well sorry keeping the
precepts and guiding of the sense doors
is the beginning of successful
contemplation and then asking the right
questions can sort of take you in the in
the right direction so why am I
suffering that can be a contemplation so
it can be any theme that you get from
the suta when the Buddha talks about
monks you know um the eyes are burning
the senses are burning it's like okay so
what did he really mean by that like
everybody make sense out of it but there
is there is a layer of there's a level
of making sense out of it intellectually
and then there's a layer of if you
actually understood it where it's
supposed to be understood you would be
free from your senses so you need to
recognize that and see that's another
contemplation you can do the the extent
of the suit application like by making
that clearer well you have a better
chance of applying it correctly so then
asking questions such as why why am I
suffering why am I liable to suffering
could I suffer if nothing is held dear
to
me is it possible to be equally liable
to pain if I'm sense restraint uh
withdrawn from un wholesome things or if
I'm just careless acting out of desires
and proliferating and scratching the it
further so pretty much uh anything that
pertains to the nature of experience
nature of Desire nature of craving
freedom from it can be can be used for
contemplation but that is the point
actively thinking about it um so that
the the meaning of it actually sinks in
so next time you won't have to ask that
question because now you understand that
attachment is the basis for suffering
you see that so from now from then
onwards whenever you
recognize uh an attachment in your
experience you don't need to go through
the motions of oh well this is suffering
this is this is the root of pain cuz if
you do means you haven't understood it
fully so you haven't contemplated
thoroughly enough but if you did
recognizing attachment will already
carry in implication this must be undone
without any further questions asked
because you already saw a direct
connection between that and pain and
liability to pain so so and and really
that's like the only method that you can
say uh that can lead you to to to
Awakening it's that diligent
contemplation of your motivation of the
nature of experience not in abstract
terms but in terms of your liabilities
your desires your your attachments and
so on as I said before I think like long
time ago when I was a Layman you know
you start learning Buddhism from all
sorts of sources you don't necessarily
know um what's right what's wrong and
yeah I was doing meditation techniques
and loads I don't know for how long as
well and and then the example I always
give was like I remember it happened on
numerous occasions obviously but it's
like so so I'm keeping the precepts I'm
sense restrained and and that's all like
and I'm meditating like you know an hour
in the morning hour in the evening cuz
that's the practice like I I pick that
up as a duty of somebody who wants to
practice you got to meditate you got to
watch your belly or NOS or whatever
Sensations I was doing it all uh and the
example I always give was like so I want
to go out with friends again nothing UNH
wholesome nothing against the precepts
just wholesome company fun get together
but if I just go out with friends
obviously I have a desire for company
for for for U for people uh I felt
guilty so it's not against the precepts
but I I knew enough to to see that it's
rooted in desire so I felt guilty so
what do I do now see how do I deal with
this well let me do my practice
duty of meditation so that then I can go
out so so then I would sit and meditate
and go out and then I would come back
and meditate and then I'm fine see I
have offset acting out of Desire through
meditation and that was my life for a
while fortunately not too long CU things
were becoming more and more apparent in
a sense that well actually see the only
reason I was doing this sense of Duty is
because I could not stop acting out of
Desire so I realized that it would have
been better off and it will be better
off if I don't sit and meditate out of
that duty at all but instead don't act
out of desire in the first place see if
you don't if I didn't go out I I
wouldn't have to be calming myself down
with the meditation people say well you
know meditation is is good it's it calms
you down well the question is why are
you disturbed in the first
place you can only you can't be
disturbed by circumstances you can't be
disturbed by the Stone Rolling and so on
you can only be disturbed by letting
Mara in who disturbs you through greed
aversion delusion so if somebody needs
meditation techniques to keep themselves
calm means they're perpetually
disturbing themselves through their own
acts and their own ignorance of their
own intentions and see if you were to
contemplate that long enough it would
sink in and you would recognize oh
important as important and unimportant
is unimportant so it's important to not
disturb myself and it's unimportant to
manage it this way or that way that's
all secondary whether I meditated for
hour did belly Bava or watch my nostrils
all of that is now secondary to the fact
that I acted out of the desire first so
if I'm not disturbing myself if I'm not
giving into the desires uh if I'm able
to contain the impulse that making me
act out of unh wholesome even if it's
not necessarily against the
precepts then if there is any
disturbance sure I'll call myself within
that but then you'll realize pretty
quickly well I am already composed
simply by not spilling out through all
these acts and so in other words instead of
acts and so in other words instead of
sitting and mechanically trying to
compensate for your lack of restraint
for your lack of understanding
compensate for that by actually sitting
down for an hour in the morning an hour
in the evening and
contemplate nature of your experience
why do you suffer how did this
disturbance come to
be all of the aspects that are relevant
to that
and do that uh every every day twice a
day because that at least can sort of
will be actually uh feeding your
perspective and uh and increasing your
understanding so then next time when
when when something unpleasant happens
or something challenging happens again
you won't need to be resorted into a
special set of circumstances where you
will stop thinking and just calm down
while this problem will remain waiting
for you you will already see through it
and see the nature of it and then you'll
be like oh yeah of course how could it
be different
attachment leads to suffering and that
is pretty clear and that's why in the
sutas as well like monks they've been
contemplating things rightly committed
to it day in day out you know he comes
back from pendapat he purifies his mind
from covetousness from greed from
aversion so where is lust in this is
there lust in this experience can lust
arise in this experience can ill will
arise in this what is the basis for ill
will oh well you know conceit anger not
wanting to deal with discomfort okay so
and then you basically take these
Reflections in all these
Myriad of directions you can do if you
start asking right questions and then
those monks who are diligent like that
would go and then it would encounter
something something shocking or
something unpleasant and it was like
they would see through it in other words
they would have done the work beforehand
and the last drop of the truth would
have been when circumstances show them
what they already understood and then it
would just sink in as like oh yeah of
course life is Dua the way out is like
what I've been doing and the mind gets
liberated there and then so people like
obviously they don't see the background
of this whole thing which is like this
intense development sens strain guarding
of the sense door contemplation day in
day out purifying your mind from the UN
wholesome States you read the suta and
you only see oh he met robers they tried
to kill him he became an Arun oh he was
so lucky I was like no no no those
circumstances just emphasized what he
already been contemplating and been
understanding so so that's really like
boils down to that like if you actually
tame your behavior aain it and then
contemplate and you will have plenty of
uh material for contemplation every
single desire every attachment
everything you don't want to give
up uh loads of stuff pick it up think
about it think about its sensation see
why you can't give it up then give it up
maybe like scare yourself even through
contemplation oh but see um I don't even
want to think about giving this who hold
on hold on why why is that why don't I
why why why am I refusing to go in that
direction well that's there is no
development there if I willingly are
choosing to turn a blind eye to
something that's going to be quite
possibly a deep attachment so oh yeah
just just give away your attachment no
no you need to understand it you can't
just throw it away because then you just
something else will take its place now
you understand that whenever there is a
phenomenon of attachment an attitude of
attachment in your experience that
equals suffering so if if I purify my
experience from any finding any safety
in any any dearness any Delight in
external things of sense objects and so
on there is no basis for suffering
anymore and the more you do it the
clearer it becomes and the confidence
will be born from it and then you won't
need any more sutas to inspire you or
the other of anothers how to contemplate
a way to go pretty much anything you
encounter you'll be seeing the
principles in it questioning if they're
unclear for that for that uh for that
the right reason for the right
purpose because if you take you know you
can sort of start by taking for granted
Mar my idea of attachment my idea of
suffering and now I need to kind of find
out and figure out the connection
between the
two but the correct
contemplation as I understand it anyway
would be more on the level of like wait
if I were to even kind of fully
understand the first word in this
sentence attachment then I would I'd be free from
attachment then I would I'd be free from
attachment and free from
well that's that's exactly see you would
probably everybody would start by these
kind of not so accurate contemplations
but yeah if you keep going in that
direction you would like hold on but do
I even know what attachment is just
saying attachment what is
it can I convey it to somebody else can
I describe it or would I need to use
some anecdotal examples can I describe
the principle behind it the universal
nature of attachment what is it can you
have attachment without
desire can you have attachment without
craving like can you have attachment
without overlooking the basic nature of your own
overlooking the basic nature of your own
experience of your own body of your own
senses I was like oh no so you will like
the more you do it and that's for me
like you need to start doing it these
contemplations will not like magically
just take you all the way to asking the
right questions and becoming an arant
through Clarity and so on it's going to
be inaccurate in the beginning but the
more you do it well the the the more
precise your own questioning will become
to the point where you don't even have
to ask the question just the way you
look at things in your experience it's
already questions are already in place
it the right direction is already in
place it so that's like through through
it so that's like through through
through through self-questioning on the
basis of guarding of the sense doors and
precepts and watching your
intentions you are you are narrowing
down to where the actual problem is um
so so yeah like the contemplation is
something the attitude of
contemplation um is something that could
certainly take you from the state of a
completely uninstructed putuj to to a
soop who now knows uh where the problem
is and knows how to how to uproot it